Marius Poulain

Nationality: French

(+33) 0626417786

Marius Poulain

Date of birth: 03/11/1996

marius.poulain@sfr.fr

Paris, FRANCE

ABOUT ME

Doctor in Biology of Interactions with three years of experience in a pest control consulting startup and over six years of **research on microbial interactions**. After a year of traveling across diverse regions worldwide, I am now **seeking to engage in stimulating and challenging research and innovation projects**. I bring a multidisciplinary mindset, a rigorous work ethic, and a strong ability to adapt and collaborate across cultures and disciplines. Proactive and creative, I value building partnerships and sharing scientific knowledge with both my team and the broader society.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Research Manager - [12/2023 – 01/2024]

French National Center for Scientific Research (CNRS) | City: **Lyon** | Country: **France** Study of the interactions between Bed Bugs and their nutritional symbiont, Wolbachia Research Director: Dr. Natacha KREMER



INRA

• Publication of a scientific article: "<u>Marius Poulain et al.</u>. <u>Development, feeding, and sex shape the relative quantity of the nutritional obligatory symbiont Wolbachia in bed bugs. Frontiers in Microbiology, 2024, 15, pp.1386458. ff10.3389/fmicb. 2024.1386458ff. ffhal-04604432".</u>

Research Manager - [10/2020 – 10/2023]

IZInovation | CNRS | INRAE | City: Lyon | Country: France

PhD Thesis on the interactions between Bed Bugs and their microbiota



- · Collaborative research between the laboratories of CNRS and INRAE, and the startup IZInovation
- Management of a research project on the new Symbiotron experimental platform
- Statistical analysis and presentations of scientific results
- Devising protocols for molecular biology, cellular biology, microscopy, and insect breeding
- Writing and publication of scientific communication articles
- Training of collaborators
- Training of clients

Internship - [01/2019 – 07/2019]

Max Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology (MPI) | City. **Bremen** | Country: **Germany** Comparative and Functional Genomics of δ -Proteobacterial Symbionts of Oligochaetes Symbiosis Department - Research Supervisor: Dr. Nicole DUBILIER



Z

Internship - [01/2018 – 07/2018]

National Research Council of Canada (NRCC) | City: Montreal | Country: Canada Characterization of the Rhizosphere Microbiome in Plants from Canadian Mining Sites Microbial Genomics Team - Research Supervisor: Dr. Charles GREER



Internship - [06/2017 – 07/2017]

French National Center for Scientific Research (CNRS) | City: **Gif-sur-Yvette** | Country: **France** Purification of the cellulose secretion complex for crystallography
Biofilm Structural Biology Team – Research Supervisor: Dr. Petya KRASTEVA



Internship - [05/2016 – 06/2016]

French Atomic Center (CEA) | City: **Saclay** | Country: **France**In silico study of the cnidarian Nitric-Oxide synthase
Oxidative Stress and Detoxification Team – Research Supervisor: Dr. Pierre DORLET



EDUCATION AND TRAINING

PhD in Biology of Interactions (EQF level 8)
Université Claude Bernard Lyon 1

[10/2020 – 12/2023]

City: Lyon | Country: France

Master of Fundamental Microbiology (EQF level 5)

Université Paris-Saclay Université de Montréal [09/2017 – 07/2019] City: **Orsay** | Country: **France**

City: Montreal | Country: Canada

UNIVERSITÉ PARIS-SACLAY Université de Montréal

(பீத்) Lyon 1

Master of Biology (EQF level 5)

Université Paris-Saclay Université de Montréal [09/2016 – 07/2019]

City: **Orsay** | Country: **France**City: **Montreal** | Country: **Canada**

UNIVERSITÉ
PARIS-SACLAY
Université
de Montréal

Bachelor of Biology and Health (EQF level 3)

Université Paris-Saclay

[09/2014 - 07/2017]

City: Orsay | Country: France



SKILLS & TOOLS

Biostatistics & Data analysis (R, Bash, Python...)

Molecular biology (Molecular Extraction, qPCR, Sequencing...)

Microbiology (Transformation, Biosynthesis, Cytometry...)

▲ Microscopy (Electronic, Confocal, Fluorescence...)

Animal breeding (Insects, Rodents...)

🐆 Immunology (ELISA, Western Blotting, Immunochemistry...)

X Project management

Transdisciplinary collaboration

Team management

Research Methodology

Consulting & training

Communication

LANGUAGE SKILLS

French: Nativ

French: Native

N N

English: C2 (1 year in Canada)



German: A2 (6 months in Germany)

MEMBERSHIPS

International Symbiosis Society - [07/2022 - 07/2023]

PhD Industrial Agreements for training through Applied Research ALMUNI - [10/2020 - Current]

HOBBIES AND INTERESTS

Global Travel - [04/2024-10/2024]

Solo-traveled worldwide for 6 months: yoga retreat in India, exploration of East Asia (Japan, South Korea...), networking in the Americas (USA, Mexico, Brazil, Peru...).

European Travel - [06/2018-07/2018]

Backpacked in several European countries (Spain, Italy, Greece, Bulgaria, Hungary, Serbia, Austria, Germany).

Archaeological Excavation Volunteering - [01/07/2016 - 31/07/2016]

Excavation of a hypogeal necropolis in a Neolithic flint mine

Sport and Activities

- Yoga [2020-Current]
- Climbing [2012-Current]
- Tennis [2002-2020]
- Member of the French Alpin Club (CAF) [2007 2014]

PUBLICATIONS

<u>Development, feeding, and sex shape the relative quantity of the nutritional obligatory symbiont Wolbachia in bed</u> bugs - [2024]

Poulain M, Rosinski E, Henri H, Balmand S, Delignette-Muller ML, Heddi A, Lasseur R, Vavre F, Zaidman-Rémy A, Kremer N. Development, feeding, and sex shape the relative quantity of the nutritional obligatory symbiont Wolbachia in bed bugs. Front Microbiol. 2024 May 7;15:1386458. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2024.1386458. PMID: 38774500; PMCID: PMC11106466.

Punaise de lit et agents pathogènes, qu'en est-il? - [2021]

Poulain M, Rametti L, Lasseur R. La punaise des lits est-elle vectrice de maladies ? Hamelin. 2021 Décembre 19; www.hamelin.info

Punaise de lit : ce que vous devez savoir - [2021]

Poulain M, Haberkorn C, Banse R, Lasseur R. Punaise de lit : ce que vous devez savoir. N&Pi. 2021 Mars-Avril; n°119; p16-18.

CONFERENCES AND SEMINARS

Regional Finalist of "My Thesis in 180 Seconds" - [23/03/2023 – 23/03/2023]

City: **Lyon** | Link: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ilJzlenWTeY&t=76s&ab_channel=UniversiteDeLyon Speaker in an international contest of scientific vulgarization.

Ecology of Sustainable Interaction Network Scientific Congress - [22/05/2023 – 26/05/2023]

City: **Poitiers** | Link: https://ebi.labo.univ-poitiers.fr/reid-2023/

Speaker on "The Nutritional Interaction between the Bed Bug and its Obligatory Symbiont, Wolbachia".

Regional Research Group in Microbiology Conferences - [13/11/2023 – 17/11/2023]

City: **Lyon** | Link: https://g-rremi.univ-lyon1.fr/spip.php?rubrique7

Speaker on "The Study of the Interaction between Bed Bugs and their Microbiota".

National Institute for Applied Science Seminar - [25/04/2023 - 25/04/2023]

City: **Lyon**

Speaker on "The Localization of Wolbachia in Bed Bugs" and poster presenter.

Regional Research Group in Microbiology Conferences - [14/11/2022 - 18/11/2022]

City: **Lyon** | Link: https://g-rremi.univ-lyon1.fr/spip.php?rubrique7

Poster presenter.

Symbiosis in the Anthropocene Era - [25/07/2022 – 29/07/2022]

City: **Lyon** | Link: https://iss10holobiont3.sciencesconf.org/

Poster presenter at the 10th International Congress of the Symbiosis Society.

REFERENCES

Fabrice VAVRE – LBBE UMR CNR 5558 – Laboratory Director: fabrice.vavre@cnrs.fr

Natacha KREMER – LBBE UMR CNRS 5558 – Research Associate: natacha.kremer@cnrs.fr

Anna ZAIDMAN-REMY - BF2I UMR INRAE 0203 – Professor: <u>anna.zaidman@insa-lyon.fr</u>

Federica CALEVRO - BF2I UMR INRAE 0203 - Laboratory Director: federica.calevro@insa lyon.fr

Romain LASSEUR – IZInovation – CEO: romain.lasseur@izinovation.com